<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "../docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY xorsymb "&#x2295;">
]>
<chapter id="des-algorithm">
  <title>The Data Encryption Standard</title>
  <para>The Data Encryption Standard, aka LUCIFER, was created by IBM
  and submitted Aug 6, 1974 as a DES candidate. In 1980 it was adopted
  formally as the standard for the banking industry. As early as 1975
  the security of DES was doubted by some, such as Martin Hellman and
  Whit Diffie because of its (relatively) small key space. In 1998 DES
  was cracked by the EFF in a total time of 56 hours. To rise to this
  task the EFF built a dedicated DES cracking machine called Deep
  Crack, which contained 27 boards of 64 chips designed to test every
  possible DES key. Until the keyspace had been exhaustively searched
  NIST continued to renew the certification of DES as a 'secure'
  algorithm. Sometime in the late 1990s (1999?), triple-DES was
  certified as a FIPS approved standard, and recommended for use
  instead of DES.</para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Keying</title>
    <para>The round keys are generated from the 64 bit secret key.
    First the 64 bit key is trimmed down to 56 bits and ordered in a
    particular manner.  The 56 bit permutation is split in half and
    each half is then taken and rotated varying amounts to generate 16
    different pairs of 28 bits. The pairs are concatenated back to
    form 56 bit values. Each one of these is then subjected to another
    permutation which picks 48 bits out of the 56. The 16 48-bit keys
    are the sub keys used during encryption.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Encryption</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Modes</title>
      <para>There are several modes that DES encryption can operate
      with. Electronic codebook, Cipher Block Chaining, Cipher
      Feedback, and Output feedback. These modes are not DES specific,
      and can be used with most block encryption methods (Skipjack is
      another FIPS algorithm that is used in all of these modes).

      <orderedlist><listitem><para>Electronic Codebook</para></listitem><listitem><para>Cipher Block Chaining</para></listitem><listitem><para>Cipher Feedback</para></listitem><listitem><para>Output Feedback</para></listitem></orderedlist>

      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Steps</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Permute the plain-text</para>
          <para>An initial permutation rearranges the plain-text, and
          splits it in half, forming a left and right half. Each part
          is 32 bits long.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The main work part of DES is 16 iterations of the
          following:</para>
          <informalexample>
            <programlisting>
            L<subscript>i</subscript> = R<subscript>i-1</subscript>
            R<subscript>i</subscript> = L<subscript>i-1</subscript> &xorsymb; f(R<subscript>i-1</subscript>, K<subscript>i</subscript>)
          </programlisting>
          </informalexample>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <sect3>
        <title>The function f</title>
        <para>The function f is a little more complex than it looks above.
          It takes as arguments a part of the current text to be operated on 
          and a round key.</para>
        <para>Each block is first expanded from 32 to 48 bits, using another
          permutation table to decide which bits get duplicated and reordered.
          The table looks like this:
          
          <informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="6" rowsep="2"><colspec colnum="1" align="right"/><colspec colnum="2" align="right"/><colspec colnum="3" align="right"/><colspec colnum="4" align="right"/><colspec colnum="5" align="right"/><colspec colnum="6" align="right"/><tbody><row><entry>32</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry></row><row><entry>4</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>9</entry></row><row><entry>8</entry><entry>9</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>11</entry><entry>12</entry><entry>13</entry></row><row><entry>12</entry><entry>13</entry><entry>14</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>16</entry><entry>17</entry></row><row><entry>16</entry><entry>17</entry><entry>18</entry><entry>19</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>21</entry></row><row><entry>20</entry><entry>21</entry><entry>22</entry><entry>23</entry><entry>24</entry><entry>25</entry></row><row><entry>24</entry><entry>25</entry><entry>26</entry><entry>27</entry><entry>28</entry><entry>29</entry></row><row><entry>28</entry><entry>29</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>31</entry><entry>32</entry><entry>1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

           With the resulting 48 bits, groups of 6 are taken and used
           to look up values in tables called &quot;S-Boxes&quot;. The 6 bits
           are used as indexes into the tables which at each location
           contains a 4 bit value. When all 8 groups of 6 have been
           transformed back to 32 bits. This is the part of the
           encryption that makes decrypting without a key hard.
           <note><para>I need to make this section a little more clear</para></note>
           </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Decryption</title>
    <para>The decryption is basically the inverse of the encryption,
    except different tables are used (inverse S-Boxes).</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>3des</title>
    <para>Triple DES is just DES applied three times, using two or
    three different keys (very important!). The first key is used to
    encrypt, the second to decrypt and the third to encrypt again
    (EDE). When we looked at simple ciphers, applying a substitution
    multiple times gained no more strength than doing it once. This is
    not the case with DES. Using 2 or 3 keys produces a encryption
    with an equivalent key of about 112 bits.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Why You Shouldn't Use DES</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Because you can use triple DES</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>DES can be broken in under 24 hours</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <sect2>
      <title>Attacking DES</title>
      <para>To defeat DES, new methods of of attack needed to be
      created. Two different types of analysis have been developed for
      the purpose of defeating DES. Both serve to provide analysis of
      block ciphers in general. It should be noted that all of the
      transformations that occur within the DES encryption are LINEAR
      except the S-box substitution. This is very important for the
      analysis of DES and other block ciphers in general.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Linear Cryptanalysis - the quick version</title>
        <para>The idea behind Linear cryptanalysis consists of assigning
      linear approximations to S box substitutions. This can be done
      by looking at the input bits and the output bits and determine
      statistical relationships between the 2 for a specific
      S-box.</para>
        <para>It is important to realize here that when looking at the
      different bits, an XOR operation is a linear operation. This can
      be seen by looking at X<subscript>1</subscript> &xorsymb; 
      X<subscript>2</subscript> = 0, which results in the conclusion
      X<subscript>1</subscript> = X<subscript>2</subscript>, and also
      X<subscript>1</subscript> &xorsymb; X<subscript>2</subscript> = 1,
      resulting in X<subscript>1</subscript> !=
      X<subscript>2</subscript>. Combinations of XOR can then be
      produced. Statements such as X<subscript>1</subscript> &xorsymb;
      X<subscript>2</subscript> = 0, and X<subscript>2</subscript> &xorsymb;
      X<subscript>3</subscript> = 0, result in
      X<subscript>1</subscript> = X<subscript>3</subscript>.</para>
        <para>Once each S-Box has been analyzed, output statistics can
      be determined by combining the expressions for each S-box that
      have been determined. This will give a probability of a certain
      input given an output (the relationships are linear remember?).
      Using this knowledge we can come up with plain-texts with high
      probabilities. How do we construct an attack using this?
      <!-- FIXME --></para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Differential Cryptanalysis - another short version</title>
        <para>Differential Cryptanalysis is very similar to Linear,
      except that Differential cryptanalysis considers the difference
      in input strings to the S-Box when correlating to the output.
      This attack basically consists of varying the input to the
      S-Boxes and determining which output bits change. How do we
      construct an attack using this? <!-- FIXME --></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
